So now we're going to do a bit of a deep dive into
the machine language of our CDC 6504 emulator. I
would suggest that if you're doing extensive work
or or even if you have some uh visual limitations
that you look at the online documentation.
It's complete and it's simple and to some
degree this lecture is really derived from the
online documentation of the CDC 6504. And so we
always are going to start and talk about the
register and just review it. Hopefully after
a couple of lectures it'll be sort of natural
to you. The program counter is the what next
instruction memory starts at zero. The accumulator
is the the best register. So it it's an the CDC
6504 is an accumulator based computer which means
that you can do more things with the accumulator
than other registers. There are flags the Z and
the N. And there's actually more in the 6502,
but Z in the N is all I've put in here. Z says,
when you're fiddling with registers, was the last
result zero or was the last result negative? And
these are used to control ifs and jumps and loops,
the Z and the N. The X and the Y are index
registers. They're just a little less capable
of the accumulator register, and they're actually
used in uh index loads, as we'll see. Instruction
memory is shown in base 2 for easy decoding.
Now the data memory I show that in hex because
mostly what we're putting in the data memory is
strings and asky characters. Okay. So the index
instructions are good for loops. And the x and y
registers are often used to control counted loops
or actually look things up within an array. And
so we have a an op code to clear the X register,
clear the Y register, add one to it, add one to
X and Y, and then subtract one from X and Y. Now,
if you think about it, the the CPU that we built
clears and increments with two instructions. So
we had an instruction of one which increments
and zero which clears. So in addition to 8bit
instructions, there are 16- bit instructions. And
so in 16- bit instructions, there is usually a
numeric value or a constant or an address that
is in the immediately following. So that means
that the program counter in this case goes up
by two. And so this the load a instruction can
take a constant value. So you can load a the
character asterisk which is a 42. And so you
see the load a instruction at memory location
zero and then the actual 42 value in this case
base 2 is at instruction one or you can basically
say we're going to do a load but the address that
we want to load from is taken from the following
eight bits. In this case we're going to load from
memory location two and the two is stored in
instruction memory location three. So these we
call these immediate and the reason we kind of
call these things immediate is the the the the
constant or the address is immediately following
the instruction in case and so these turn into
16- bit instructions. You could see it as you
load one instruction in and there would probably
be both a current instruction register and an
immediate register. And you would notice that this
instruction that we just loaded has an immediate
and so we'd load both of those things and then
have them in the CPU to to work. So loading and
storing operations are important. So you can
load into the A register, the X register and the
Y register. And you can store into the A register,
X register and Y register. And you can either load
a constant like set a to zero load a hashtag zero
or you can say go get memory location you know
F3 and load that in. Okay. And so those are the
instructions that do loading and storing. Now when
we start dealing with arrays we have the we can
use the X and the Y. So we can say this address is
kind of the beginning of the array and then X and
Y are the offset in the array. So you you start
seeing that you can set x to zero. You can load
something from a starting point in memory plus
x and then you can add one to zero and then load
something again from that same place in memory
plus x and then x become and y are really well
designed to use as iteration variables. And then
this is where the accumulator is important where
the accumulator is the register that can do the
most things. So we can't add arbitrary values. So
we can't add we can add one to X and Y registers
but we can't add five. So ADC hashtag five adds
five to it. So the same for subtraction. And
that you can either add an immediate value like
a constant or you can go into some memory and
grab that memory and add it to the accumulator.
So you can see it says ACC equals ACC plus memory
bracket address. That means that we're adding in
the data memory at the position that's addressed.
But the address it's an immediate instruction and
the next one is the address that we're going to
add. So adding and subtracting is the accumulator.
Now the everything that is adding, subtracting,
loading, storing, whatever it's doing to whatever
register sets the Z and the N flags. And
so it just as part of the final putting
the value into the register, it sets Z and N. So
if the value we put in to the register was zero,
the Z flag will be a one. It'll be set. If the
value we put in was 42, the Z flag will be zero.
And the same with positive and negative. Negative
numbers are numbers that have the first bit,
the tie bit one. We we're not doing too much,
we won't be doing too much with negative in
this class. will mostly be setting the zero
but you can do like less than or equal with
the negative. So combinations of uh Z and N can do
greater than or equal, less than or equal, etc.,
etc. And so there is a uh special instruction
called the compare instruction that says, hey,
let's check to see if the accumulator equals five.
But you're really saying five accumulator check
them. It's kind of like a subtraction without
actually doing the subtraction. And then set
subtract set the Z and N flags from the result of
the subtraction and then throw away the result of
the subtraction. So that's what the comparison
operators are. Okay? And so you can compare
um the accumulator, the X, and the Y. So there's
no if statement in machine code. All there are are
conditional jumps. And so that you'll have to get
used to it. When I started in Forran, everything
was a go-to before we had structure ifs, if then
else. That that's not in machine code. There is a
conditional jump, which we'll talk about. And the
way you get the conditional jumps to activate is
every instruction that changes a register and the
compare instructions with don't change registers
set the result flags. There's a Z, which is was
the result zero or not? And then the N is was
the result negative or not. And so if the result
is zero, the Z is one and the N is zero because
Z is not negative. If the result is positive,
Z is zero because it's not zero and N is zero
because it's not negative. And if the result is
negative, Z is zero and one is negative. And yes,
you can use these together to create greater than,
greater than or equal to, equal, less than, less
than or equal to. So that's kind of what you're
thinking about, right? is uh how to implement what
we think of as the traditional logical operators
in a highle language. So the closest we have to an
if statement is a compare and then a conditional
jump. And so there are four instructions,
right? There's more of them, but these are
the four that matter. The BEQ branch if equal,
that means the Z flag is set. B ne branch if
not equal mean means the Z flag is clear and
then branch minus BMI and then BPL means branch
plus. So for example here's a little tiny bit of
code that we can do an uppercase. We're going
to convert a lowercase to uppercase and leave
uppercase alone. Okay. So we do hashtag quote
p quote which is the ASCII value for 'p'. Now,
normally we'd read this from input, but we're not
going to. We're just going to hard-code the the v
the value we're going to convert. Then we're going
to compare that to the ASCII value for a. So that
comparison then sets the z and the n. And then
we're going to say BMI to location 08, which we'll
talk about this in a second, how that works, how
you know that that's 08. That's kind of tricky.
But that's an address in instruction memory, the
08. And then if it's minus, we will skip the next
instruction. But if it's not minus, we're going
to subtract hex 20 because that's converting to
lower case. If you look at the ASCII table, you
see that the the difference between an uppercase
A and a lowercase A um is 20. The lowercase A is
20 hex higher than an uppercase A. And then that
BMI is 08. If it's already uppercase, meaning
it's a lower number, that jumps to the BRK and
the program stops. You can think of this as if
the accumulator is less than the letter A, we're
going to skip the next instruction. And if the
if we don't skip, we're going to subtract 20 hex.
And if we do skip, we're done. And then in the
accumulator will be the uppercase letter whether
or not the original letter that was loaded into
the accumulator was uppercase or lowercase. And
so this is where flowcharts come back. Remember I
said flowcharts are not cool. Although if you ask
AI often flowcharts are cool. They're very retro.
Well the key to flowcharts is that they work
exactly like assembly and machine language. So if
we look at the first instruction which is loading
the accumulator with the letter the lowercase P
then we're doing a compare instruction. So the
compare instruction is not something we think of
in a high level language. We're asking a question.
We're like compare the accumulator to a and set
the flags. That's what the compare instruction
is doing. Is accumulator equal to less than or
greater than a? And so then we say was the result
of that particular compare a BMI negative because
BMI means is the N flag set and if the N flag is
set we're going to jump to to instruction memory
location08. If not we're going to fall through.
And by the way, the actual dollar 08 is in the
immediately following uh instruction memory.
And so where to jump is the 08. Then if we don't
jump, we're going to subtract 20 hex. And the 20
is also in immediate memory. And then the place
the program stops is at instruction memory 0x08.
So the way if you're doing this by hand, you'd
actually kind of leave instruction memory 05
blank, lay everything else out, and then you
see where 0x08, the halt ends up, and then you
would go copy that back in to the 0x05 memory
location. That seems painful. Painful even for
eight instructions. Thankfully, we have this
thing called assembly language. So there's no
need to compute these instructions by hand. And
so if you look at the BMI in this code, you say
BMI skip and then right before the instruction
that you want to skip to, you put a little label
with a colon. So skip colon. Now, it turns out
that just like I told you on the last slide,
the assembler is making two passes. It literally
is assembling all the code and remembering where
it needs to change addresses. So it kind of keeps
track of that's going to wherever skip turns out
to be because skip could be later. So it has to do
it all. Has to lay it all out. Has to figure out
where it's going to go in the memory and then it
has to go back and replace the skip with the eight
hex so that it knows what it's doing. But for us,
we don't care. We write assembly language. We use
labels. and the whole notion that you've got to
do two passes by hand, we just write assembly
language. And so our larger example codes will be
assembly language. And so the jumps, like I said,
are far simpler than if logic. So in addition to
the BEQ, the B branch equal, branch not equal,
branch minus, and branch plus, we also have an
unconditional jump. That's ignoring, you know,
jump to an address that just says don't look at
the flags, just unconditionally jump. But just
think about this for a second. The PC, the program
counter is itself a register. So even though we
have these op codes that say branch, sure, or
jump, in a sense, you could think of these as
just a set of the PC. If the in if if we had a
assembly language that said set PC to this address
then that would mean that the PC the next time it
would retrieve an instruction would go to where
it's at. So you can think of a jump as set the PC
to this address or a jump conditional says if this
condition is true set the PC to this address and
of course these are all 16 bit instructions and
so that address is in the immediately following uh
memory uh memory location. Okay. So there are also
no for and while loops in machine language and so
we have to construct them with these comparisons
and conditional branching. So I'm not going to
bother showing you the machine language for this.
The emulator will allow you to see that. Um I'm
just going to show you the assembly. So the in
the on the left is assembly language and assembly
language is a textual language that is not zeros
and ones but there is a one-to-one correspondence
that every single assembly language statement
turns into directly into machine language. Now
it might be a 8-bit machine language or a 16-
bit machine language and the assembler which
is a program that converts this text to machine
language. The assembler knows all the rules, the
syntax of the pound sign five. So really while
we have been talking about machine language, we
mostly been talking about assembly language. So
let's take a look at a really simple for loop.
Now this for loop doesn't do anything. It's just
constructing this for loop or a while loop. It's
a top- tested loop. So if we go through this,
the first thing we do and and I mentioned that
X registers are good for loops and arrays.
First thing we're going to do is we're going to
clear the X register. Then we're going to have
a label that says here's a place we're going
to come back to. But that doesn't take up any
memory. That just is something that the assembler
is going to remember that location, wherever that
location is. Then we're going to compare the X
register to five. Like that's saying, huh, hey,
let's just look at X. Let's look at five. And
then set the Z and the N flags. And BEQ to end.
end is a label in this case. So if x equals 5,
we're going to jump to the end label. If we're
not jumping, we're coming through. We're going
to add one to x, which is the inx instruction
or x= x + one. Now in this right hand side,
these x's are not really just any old variable.
That means the x register. So there's only like
the accumulator and the X and the Y and program
counter and instruction register, but they're just
these are not variables. These are just plain old
registers. So after the INX instruction, we do
an unconditional jump and you can see that on
the flowchart on the right hand side perfectly
represented to jump back to loop. Now where is
loop? What number is loop? We don't know and
we don't care. But the assembler is going to
turn that before it gets loaded into the memory
as machine language. Loop becomes a number just
like end becomes a number. So we jump to the top
of the loop and you can see that we added one to
X and then we compare it to X. We we check the
branch which does in the second time around it
goes straight down and adds one again. So you
can see this is a for loop that's going to go
round and round and round until X is equal to five
and then it's going to jump to end and at end the
program is going to halt. In the next section
we're going to go into we're not going to worry
quite so much about the machine language. We're
going to worry more about the assembly language.
So we can talk about building simple algorithms
in machine language but writing them in assembly
language. And so if you look at the summary
of the machine language we've talked about so
far. This is not all of them but they're kind of
simple. You load, you compare, you jump, etc. And
you can branch and jump and clear and increment
and stop. And it's a real really simple thing.
And it is both simple and powerful, but it's
actually super verbose because of its simplicity.